A Guide to the Papers of the Muller-Jones Surgical Society, 1966-2011
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Papers of the Muller-Jones Surgical Society, 1966-2011
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-49
5 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 2.25 feet, 48 folders
Historical Collections
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Wayne Ferguson.
Biographical/Historical Information
The William H. Muller, Jr. Surgical Society was founded in 1968 largely at the instigation of Drs. Peter Hairston, John Vansant, and Gardner W. Smith. The society was formed to honor Dr. Muller, the S. Hurt Watts Professor and Chairman of the Department of Surgery at the University of Virginia from 1954 to 1982; provide a means for the social and scientific reunion of former surgical residents who served under Dr. Muller; to provide a forum for presentations of the members of the Society; and to promote a spirit of common purpose and camaraderie among the members of the society. The first meeting was held in Charleston, South Carolina, in the spring of 1969. Subsequent meetings have occurred every two years. The society was originally open to all who had completed General, Thoracic and Thoracic-Cardiiovascular Surgical Residencies at the University of Virginia under Dr. Muller who first came to the University in 1954.
In 1971 the name was amended to the Muller Surgical Society. By the time of Dr. Muller's resignation as Department Chair, the decision was made to continue to offer membership to those completing surgical residencies at the University of Virginia. In 1985 the members of the Society formally established a Muller Surgical Society Eminent Scholars Program Professorship in Surgery. By 2003 the Society had changed its name to the Muller-Jones Surgical Society to include Rayford Scott Jones, Chair of the Department of Surgery at the University of Virginia from 1981 to 2001.
In 2009 the constitution was amended to reflect the change in name to the Muller-Jones Surgical Society and the purpose was amended to stipulate that the Society was to operated exclusively for charitable, scientific and educational purposes with the goal or honoring both Dr. Muller and Dr. Jones. In addition to former surgical residents, all current or former surgical faculty members were officially offered the opportunity to participate.
Scope and Content
The collection includes correspondence, minutes of meetings, programs of the biennial Society meetings, and organizational constitutions and by-laws.
Arrangement
Box one contains the programs of the biennial meetings, a guest book, and constitutions and by-laws. Boxes two through five contain correspondence and some minutes arranged by date.
Contents List
- By-laws and constitutions, 1968-2009, n.d. (Box-folder 001-001)
- Guest book for biennial meetings, 1975-1987 (Box-folder 001-002)
- Society biennial programs: first through tenth, 1969-1987 (Box-folder 001-003)
- Society biennial programs: eleventh through twentieth, 1989-2007 (Box-folder 001-004)
- Society biennial programs: twenty-first through twenty-second, 2009-2011 (Box-folder 001-005)
- Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 002-001)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 002-002)
- Correspondence, 1969 (Box-folder 002-003)
- Correspondence, 1970 (Box-folder 002-004)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 002-005)
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box-folder 002-006)
- Correspondence, 1973 (Box-folder 002-007)
- Correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 002-008)
- Correspondence, 1975 (Box-folder 002-009)
- Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 002-010)
- Correspondence, 1977 (Box-folder 003-001)
- Correspondence, 1978 (Box-folder 003-002)
- Correspondence, 1979 (Box-folder 003-003)
- Correspondence, 1980 (Box-folder 003-004)
- Correspondence, 1981 (Box-folder 003-005)
- Correspondence, 1982 (Box-folder 003-006)
- Correspondence and minutes, 1983 (Box-folder 003-007)
  Dr. R. Scott Jones, new Chair of the Department of Surgery is accepted as an honorary member of the Society. Plans are underway for a suitable memorial to Dr. Muller--a named chair of surgery.
- Correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 003-008)
  The Society is looking into becoming an IRS designated non-profit so that it could receive tax-deductible contributions towards the proposed Professorship in Dr. Muller's name.
- Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 004-001)
- Correspondence, 1986 (Box-folder 004-002)
- Correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 004-003)
- Correspondence, 1988 (Box-folder 004-004)
- Correspondence, 1989 (Box-folder 004-005)
- Correspondence, 1990 (Box-folder 004-006)
- Correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 004-007)
- Correspondence, 1992 (Box-folder 004-008)
  Some of the correspondence relates to the question of inviting UVa Department of Surgery faculty, whether they were residents under Dr. Muller or not, to become members of the Society.
- Correspondence, 1993 (Box-folder 004-009)
- Correspondence, 1994 (Box-folder 004-010)
  A letter from Robert M. Carey states that the William H. Muller, Jr. Professorship in Surgery Fund was created in 1992 by the combination of the Distinguished Professorship in Surgery and the Muller Society Professorship in Surgery. Irving Kron, the chief of thoracic cardiovascular surgery has held the Muller chair since 1990.
- Correspondence, 1995 (Box-folder 004-011)
- Correspondence, 1996 (Box-folder 004-012)
- Correspondence and abstracts, 1997 (Box-folder 004-013)
- Correspondence, 1998 (Box-folder 004-014)
- Correspondence, 1999 (Box-folder 004-015)
- Correspondence, 2001 (Box-folder 004-016)
- Correspondence, 2002 (Box-folder 004-017)
- Correspondence, 2003 (Box-folder 004-018)
- Correspondence, 2004 (Box-folder 004-019)
- Correspondence, 2005 (Box-folder 004-020)
- Correspondence, 2006 (Box-folder 004-021)
- Correspondence, 2007 (Box-folder 005-001)
- Correspondence, 2008 (Box-folder 005-002)
- Correspondence, 2009 (Box-folder 005-003)
- Correspondence, 2011 (Box-folder 005-004)